<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="file:/usr/share/xml/geekodoc/rng/geekodoc5-flat.rnc"
   type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>

<!DOCTYPE article
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "generic-entities.ent">
    %entities;
]>
<!--
Confluence page:
https://confluence.suse.com/x/8IEnGw
-->

<article version="5.1" xml:lang="en" xml:id="art-sol-activedirectory"
  xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
  xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
  <title>&sap; and Windows Active Directory Integration</title>
  <subtitle>&sles4sapreg; · &slereg; &hasi;</subtitle>
  <info>
    <abstract>
      <para>
        This article offers some guidance for &sap; administrators, who wants to install and manage SAP HANA and High-Avaibility components running on SUSE Linux 
        managed centrally via a Microsoft active directory server.
      </para>
      <para>
        In most Microsoft environments, the Active Directory domain is the central hub for user information,
        which means that there needs to be some way for Linux systems to access that user information for authentication requests.
        The AD integration main goal is to provide the ability to a Microsoft Admin to manage all the important HA/SAP users authentication cecentrally via Microsoft Active Directory server,
        instead of having local users to Linux machines and having to log in and manage them separately.
      </para>
    </abstract>
  </info>

  <note>
    <title>About Official &suse; Support</title>
    <para>
      Realmd component is supported starting from &productname; 15 SP2.
    </para>
  </note>



  <sect1 xml:id="sec-sol-active-dir-concept-overview">
    <title>Realmd</title>
    <para>
       realmd is an on demand system DBus service, which allows callers to configure network authentication and domain membership in a standard way. 
       realmd discovers information about the domain or realm automatically and does not require complicated configuration in order to join a domain.
       For more information, see <link
        xlink:href="https://www.freedesktop.org/software/realmd/"/> 
    </para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 xml:id="sec-joining-microsoft-domain">
    <title>Join a SLE Machine to a Microsoft Domain Before Installation of HANA</title>
    <procedure>
      <step>
        <para>
         On you &productname; 15 SP2 system install the following packages:
        </para>
        <screen>zypper in realmd adcli sssd sssd-tools sssd-ad samba-client</screen>
      </step>
    </procedure>
    <para>
      The above procedure is automatically done by each of the &salt; formulas
      described in <xref linkend="art-sol-automation"/>.
    </para>
  </sect1>


  <xi:include href="common_copyright_quick.xml"/>
  <xi:include href="common_legal.xml"/>
</article>
