<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
    %entities;
]>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0"
   xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
   xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
   xml:id="cha.hana-sr.scenario">
 <title>Supported Scenarios and Prerequisites</title>
 <para>
  For the first version of the SAPHanaSR resource agent software package, we
  limit the support to the following scenarios and parameters:
 </para>
 <itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Two-node clusters
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    The cluster must include a valid STONITH method
   </para>
   <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Any STONITH mechanism supported by SLE 11 HAE (like sdb,IPMI) is
      supported with SAPHanaSR.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      This guide is focusing on the sbd fencing method as this is hardware
      independent.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      If you use sbd as fencing mechanism you need one or more shared
      drives. For productive environments we recommend more than one sbd
      device.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Scale-Up (single-box to single-box) system replication
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Both nodes are in the same network segment (layer 2)
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Technical users and groups such as sidadm are defined locally in the
    Linux system
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Name resolution of the cluster nodes and the virtual IP address must be
    done locally on all cluster nodes
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Time synchronization between the cluster nodes using NTP
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    There is no other SAP HANA system(like QA) on the replicating node which
    needs to be stopped during takeover.
   </para>
   <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Beginning with version 0.149 of SAPHanaSR this is not a technical
      limit any more, but this scenario still needs to be described and
      tested in detail.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Such configurations are only supported for PoCs or after properly
      testing in the implementation project.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    There is only one system replication for the SAP HANA database.
   </para>
   <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      This means only single-tier not a multi-tier setup.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Chains (like A => B -> C) are currently only supported for PoCs or
      after properly testing in the implementation project, starting with
      version 0.149 of the resource agent.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Both SAP HANA instances have the same SAP Identifier (SID) and Instance-
    Number
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    If the cluster nodes are installed in different data centers or data
    center areas, the environment must match the requirements of the SLE HAE
    cluster product. This in special means the network latencies between the
    nodes and the recommended maximum distance. Please review our product
    documentation for SLE HAE about those recommendations.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Automated resistration of a failed primary after takeover
   </para>
   <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      As a good starting configuration for PoCs and projects we recommend to
      switch-off the automated registration of a failed primary. The setup
      <literal>AUTOMATED_REGISTER="false"</literal> is also the default
      since version 0.139. In this case you need to register a failed
      primary after a takeover manulally using SAP tools like hanastudio or
      hdbnsutil.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      For optimal automation we recommend
      <literal>AUTOMATED_REGISTER="false"</literal>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Automated start of SAP HANA instances during system boot must be
    switched off.
   </para>
  </listitem>
 </itemizedlist>
 <para>
  You need at least SAPHanaSR version 0.149.
 </para>
 <note>
  <title>Valid STONITH Method</title>
  <para>
   Without a valid STONITH method the complete cluster is unsupported and
   will not work properly.
  </para>
 </note>
 <para>
  If you need to implement a different scenario we strongly recommend to
  define a PoC with SUSE. This PoC will focus in testing the existing
  solution in your scenario. The limitation of most of the above items is
  mostly due to testing limits.
 </para>
 <para>
  The resource agent supports SAP HANA in System replication beginning with
  SAP HANA version 1.0 SPS 7 patch level 70.
 </para>
 <para>
  Beside SAP HANA you need SAP hostagent to be installed on your system.
 </para>
</chapter>
