<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE preface
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
    %entities;
]>
<preface xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.0"
   xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
   xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
   xml:id="pre.hana-sr">
 <title>About This Guide</title>
 <para>
  &sles4sapreg; is the reference platform for SAP's software development. It
  is optimized in various ways for SAP applications. This guide provides
  detailed information about installing and customizing &sles4sap;.
 </para>
 <sect1>
  <title>Introduction</title>

<!-- Make this an "overview" later... -->

  <para>
   “SAP customers invest in SAP HANA” is the conclusion reached by a
   recent market study carried out by Pierre Audoin Consultants (PAC). In
   Germany alone, half of the companies expect SAP HANA to become the
   dominant database platform in the SAP environment. In many cases, the
   “SAP Business Suite® powered by SAP HANA” scenario is already being
   discussed in concrete terms.
  </para>

  <para>
   Naturally, SUSE is also accommodating this development by providing SUSE
   Linux Enterprise Server for SAP Applications – the recommended and
   supported operating system for SAP HANA. In close collaboration with SAP
   and hardware partners, therefore, SUSE will provide two resource agents
   for customers to ensure the high availability of SAP HANA system
   replications.
  </para>

  <sect2>
   <title>Two Replication Scenarios</title>
   <para>
    The current first phase of the project includes the architecture and
    development of scale-up scenarios, which will be tested together with
    SAP in the coming weeks. System replication will help to replicate the
    database data from one computer to another computer in order to
    compensate for database failures (single-box replication).
   </para>
   <figure xml:id="fig.hana-sr.in-cluster">
    <title>SAP HANA System Replication in the Cluster</title>
    <mediaobject>
     <imageobject role="fo">
      <imagedata fileref="hana_sr_in_cluster.png" width="85%" format="PNG"/>
     </imageobject>
     <imageobject role="html">
      <imagedata fileref="hana_sr_in_cluster.png" width="85%" format="PNG"/>
     </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
   </figure>
   <para>
    This will be followed by a second project phase involving an extension
    for scale-out scenarios (multibox replication). With this mode of
    operation, internal SAP HANA high-availability (HA) mechanisms and the
    resource agent must work together or be coordinated with each other.
   </para>
   <para>
    SUSE has implemented the scale-up scenario with the SAPHana resource
    agent (RA), which performs the actual check of the SAP HANA database
    instances and is configured as a master/slave resource. In the scale-up
    scenario, the master assumes responsibility for the SAP HANA databases
    running in primary mode, and the slave is responsible for instances that
    are operated in synchronous (secondary) status.
   </para>
   <para>
    To make configuring the cluster as simple as possible, SUSE also
    developed it's SAPHanaTopology resource agent. This runs on all nodes of
    an SLE 11 HAE cluster and gathers information about the statuses and
    configurations of SAP HANA system replications. It is designed as a
    normal (stateless) clone.
   </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2>
   <title>Customers Receive Complete Package</title>
   <para>
    With both the SAPHana and SAPHanaTopology resource agents, customers
    will therefore be able to integrate SAP HANA system replications in
    their cluster. This has the advantage of enabling companies to use not
    only their business-critical SAP systems but also their SAP HANA
    databases without interruption while noticeably reducing needed budgets.
    SUSE provides the extended solution together with best practices
    documentation.
   </para>
   <para>
    SAP and hardware partners who do not have their own SAP HANA
    high-availability solution will also benefit from this new SUSE Linux
    development.
   </para>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>
 <sect1>
  <title>Additional Documentation and Resources</title>

  <para>
   Chapters in this manual contain links to additional documentation
   resources that are either available on the system or on the Internet.
  </para>

  <para>
   For the latest documentation updates, see
   <link xlink:href="http://www.suse.com/documentation"/>.
  </para>

  <para>
   You can also find numerous whitepapers, a best-practices guide, and other
   resources at the &sles4sap; resource library:
   <link xlink:href="https://www.suse.com/products/sles-for-sap/resource-library/"/>.
  </para>
 </sect1>
 <xi:include href="common_intro_feedback_i.xml" parse="xml"/>
 <xi:include href="common_intro_typografie_i.xml" parse="xml"/>
</preface>
