<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//Novell//DTD NovDoc XML V1.0//EN" "novdocx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % NOVDOC.DEACTIVATE.IDREF "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
%entities;
]>
<sect1 id="s4s.configuration">

 <title>Configuring &sles4sap;</title>
 <para>
 </para>

 <sect2 id="s4s.config.page-cache">

  <title>Kernel: Page-Cache Limit</title>

  <para>
  </para>

  <variablelist>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>Problem</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      The kernel swaps out rarely accessed memory pages in order to use
      freed memory pages as cache to speed up file system operations,
      for instance during backup operations.
     </para>
     <para>
      Some SAP solutions use large amounts of memory for accelerated
      access to business data. Parts of this memory are very seldom
      accessed. When a user request then needs to access paged out
      memory, the response time is poor.  It is being even worse, when
      an SAP solution running on Java incurs a Java garbage
      collection. The system starts heavy page-in (disc I/O) activity
      and incurs poor response time for an extended period of time.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>

   <varlistentry>
    <term>Solution</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      A new kernel tune option has been introduced that allows the
      system administrator to limit the amount of page-cache that the
      kernel uses when there is competition between application memory
      and page-cache.  This option tells the kernel that once the
      page-cache is filled to the configured limit, application memory
      is more important and should thus not be paged out. No pages will
      be paged out if the memory footprint of the workload plus the
      configured page cache limit do not exceed the amount of physical
      RAM in the system.
     </para>
     <para>
      For more information, see SAP Note 1557506: Linux paging
      improvements <ulink
      url="https://service.sap.com/sap/support/notes/1557506"/>.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
 </sect2>
 <!-- ==================================================================== -->
 <sect2 id="s4s.config.ports">

  <title>Ports Configuration</title>

  <para>
   SAP applications require many open ports and port ranges.  The exact numbers
   depend on the selected instances, for example: 3200-3399, 3600, 4700-4899,
   7200-7299, 50000-59999.  It is also required to open 1128 and 1129 (TCP and
   DP), all the ports needed for the used databases (Oracle, DB2, MaxDB,
   Sybase).
  </para>
 </sect2>

<!--
 <sect2>
  <title>For More Information</title>

  <para>For more information about tuning &sls; see the SLES &tuning;.</para>
 </sect2>
-->
</sect1>
